Register of the George M. Vesselago Papers, 1904-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
George M. Vesselago Papers,
1904-1970
75062
Vesselago, George M., 1892-
8 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope 3.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, clippings, and photographs, relating to Russian naval operations during World War I and the Russian Revolution and Civil War
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Russia. Voennyi flot; Petroleum--Soviet Union; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations; Russia; Soviet Union; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Naval operations; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920
Biographical Note
George M. Vesselago, 1892 -
1892, September 29 Born, Kronstadt, Russia
1905-1918 Served in the Imperial Russian Navy with the last rank being Lieutenant-Commander
1919-1920 Served with White Russian forces in Civil War
1920 Quartermaster, U.S.S. Santa Clara, from India to New York
1920-1921 Inspector of ammunition at Eddystone Plant of Baldwin Locomotive Works (Pennsylvania)
1921-1925 Employed by Cortez Oil Corporation
1926-1954 Staff Engineer with Day and Zimmerman, Inc.
1954-1964 Associated with Edward N. Hay and Associates, Inc.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1919-1970. (Box Box No. 1-6)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject File, 1904-1970. (Box Box No. 5-8)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, lists, charts, notes, printed matter, clippings, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1968. (Box Box No. 8)
  Speeches and writings by G.M. Vesselago, arranged alphabetically by title.
- Miscellany. (Box Box No. 8)
  Miscellaneous notes, printed matter, etc.
- Photographs.
  See photo file card index.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1919-1970
  - Alexandroff, K., 1922 (Box 1)
  - Andrei, 1922, 1923, 1931 (Last name unknown)
  - Arushievaskaia, Z., 1922
  - Baruch, Bernard M., 1933
  - Bensel, Otto, 1927
  - Betcher, George, 1927
  - Biddle, Francis, 1942
  - Bill, 1935
  - Boris, 1922-1923 (Last name unknown)
  - Bossé, Anna, 1933
  - Brown Brothers Harriman and Company, 1923
  - Bukowski, Peter I., n.d.
  - Chaiko, M., 1921-1922
  - Chelouchin, Stefan, 1924
  - Chernov, Aleksei M., 1921
  - Cook, Clara, 1925
  - Corfino, George P., 1922
  - Crolius, Fred J., 1925
  - Dembrovskii, M., 1922
  - Demidoff, Pavel, 1922
  - Dillon, V. I., 1922
  - Elledge, G.E., 1922
  - Fedorov, K. V., 1921
  - Gard, Alexis K., 1944
  - Garin, A., 1927
  - Golitsyn, Nikolai, n.d.
  - Golovchenko, A.P., 1923
  - Grandmother, 1934
  - Howe, Helen, n.d.
  - Iakovlev, Ermogen and Feofilakii, 1921
  - Iakovleva, Lidiia, 1922
  - Ivanov, V., 1921
  - Izidin, B., 1921-1922
  - Johnson, D.W., 1921
  - Karpenko, Boris, 1921
  - Kititzyn, M.A., 1921-1923, 1927
  - Kliagin, N., 1922
  - Konstantin Vasil'evich, 1921
  - Kozlova, E., 1925
  - Kuraev, 1921 (first name unknown)
  - La Roches, Nikolai S., 1933
  - Lewis, Adler, and Laws (Attorneys), 1927
  - Loukine, Aleksandr, 1933
  - Lysoeff, K., n.d.
  - McCully, 1921 (first name unknown)
  - McDonald, Nina M., 1970
  - Machold, William F., 1968
  - Makaroff, Wadim, 1922
  - Mania, 1921-1922, 1925 (last name unknown)
  - Martin, Hugh S., 1924
  - Maslovsky, E., 1932
  - Matskevich, G., 1921-1922
  - Meidelkeva, Sofia, 1922, 1925
  - Meirer, George A., 1921-1922
  - Miller, Dr. T. Grier, 1927, 1933
  - Mishtovt, Illarion V., 1922
  - Mother, 1921-1943
  - Nedbal', Nikolai A., 1922 (Box 2)
  - Nemova, M., 1922
  - Nikolski, A., 1922
  - Nishchenkov, A., 1923
  - Parkes, 1921 (first name unknown)
  - Pavlov, A., n.d.
  - Perfilieff, Captain V., 1921
  - Pini, Vladimir, 1933
  - Polivanov, M., 1922
  - Poltavskii, B., 1921-1922
  - Proskuriakov, A., 1922, 1924
  - Pushkarev, Kirill N, 1922
  - Reed, 1933 (first name unknown)
  - Rohtast, Peter, 1925
  - Romanov, Vasili, 1968
  - Russian Historical Archive and Repository (Stanford), 1968
  - Russian Students' Christian Association in the U.S.A., 1922
  - Safonoff, Sergei, 1923
  - Selesneff, D., 1922-1923
  - Sergei Vladimirovich, 1921 (last name unknown)
  - Shcherbachev, Oleg A., 1921
  - Shelley, John, 1921, 1923
  - Shelukin, Stefan, 1925
  - Shestov, A. & L., 1927
  - Shichiko, P., 1921
  - Smirnov, Mikhail I., 1922
  - South American Gulf Oil Company, 1925
  - Sovinsky, V.N., 1930
  - Stebline-Kamensky, J., 1922-23, 1931
  - Strakhovsky, Leonid, 1922-23, 1930-33
  - Strekalovskii, 1921 (first name unknown)
  - Tatishchev, Alexis, 1931
  - Taylor, W.P., 1921-1924
  - Taylor, Mrs. W.P., 1921-1925
  - Taube, George N., 1952
  - Thayer, Elizabeth H., n.d.
  - Timofeev, N., 1922
  - Trofimoff, Vladimir I., 1921
  - Trotter, Elizabeth F., 1925, 1927
  - Tuchkov, A., 1921
  - Tuttle, 1925 (first name unknown)
  - Vasiliev, Sergei, 1921
  - Vedeniapinskii, V., 1922
  - Vesselago, Mikhail, 1921-23, 1925
  - Vesselago, Sofia, 1921-1935
  - Vesselago, Sofia, 1928-1935 (Box 3.)
  - Von Mohrenschildt, Dimitri S., 1922
  - Voronin, 1921 (first name unknown)
  - Watson, P.B., 1925
  - Witherey, W.L., 1922
  - Wiren, Alexis, 1922
  - Yanenko, M., 1924
  - Zakharchenko, K., 1921-1923
  - Zweguintzoff, N., 1921-1922
  - Zweguintzoff, Sofia, 1921-1928
  - Zweguintzoff, Sofia, 1923-1925, 1927-1928 (Box 4.)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1919-1920
    - 1920-1921 (Box 5.)
    - 1921-1932 (Box 6.)
    - undated
- Subject File, 1904-1970
  - Address book (Box 7.)
  - Aguada, Mexico
    - Commissioner meetings, April 11, 1922
    - Report No. 55, Sucesiones, February 13, 1922
    - Work report No. 87, June 9, 1923
  - Association of Former Russian Naval Officers in America
  - Biographical data
  - Birth of daughter, Sofia, 1933
  - Business matters
  - Certificates, letters of introduction, etc.
  - Cleland, Robert G., Background of the Latest Mexican Revolution, undated
  - East, E.M., Oversea Politics and the Food Supply, undated
  - Fedotoff-White, D., excerpts from Survival, 1951
  - Financial matters
  - Goonin, Sergei T., America and Russia, reprint from University of Pennsylvania Red and Blue, March 1922
  - Immigration to the U.S., 1927
  - Kennan, George
    - Complications in Murmansk, undated
    - The Worth in April and May, undated
  - Military Correspondence file, 1918-1919
  - Naval Officers Group in Harbin, China, 1925
  - Pavlov, A.N., Our Class (in Russian), Morskiia Zapiski (The Naval Record) [New York], Vol. IX, December 1951
  - Precision Topics (Falls River, Massachussets), 1942-1943
  - Russia
    - Petroleum, 1904-1923
    - Revolution and Civil War
  - Russian Red Cross
  - Russian Sholar, edited by the Russian Students Christian Association in the U.S.A., Nov 2, 1922
  - Russian Student Conference at Silver Bay, New York, 1922
  - Selesneff, D.D., In the Bosphorus (in French), La Revue Maritime, No. 239, January 1967
  - Stebline-Kamensky, I.
    - Break-Through in the Bosphorus on Patrol Boat No. 324 (in Russian), Chasovoi (Asnieres, France), No. 64, September 1931
    - Mining Warfare, abstracts from an article in La Renaissance, August 12, 1929 (copy in Russian) (Box 8.)
  - Strakhovsky, Leonid I.
    - Diplomatic Aspects of American Intervention in Siberia, 1918-1920, undated
    - The Russian Origins of the American Intervention in North Russia in 1918-1919, undated
  - Title Situation in the Aguada, report No. 54, February 7, 1922
  - Ukhta Petroleum, 1918
  - United Gas Company
    - Brochure
    - Cost Control for Electric and Gas Utilities, February 26, 1932
  - Varnek, P.A., The Russian North During World War I (in Russian), Morskiia Zapiski (The Naval Record) [New York], Volume VIII, Nos. 3/4, December 1950
  - Voevodsky, Jack
  - Volnaia Kuban (Free Kuban), No. 26, May 1, 1925
  - Will, February 1964
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1968
  - Assemblies, undated (Box 8.)
  - Awakening in Khronstadt, undated
  - The Davis-Davis Episode, undated
  - Drillings in the Aguada, January 7, 1924
  - Episodes Recalled (My Recollections), July 1968
  - A Few Episodes from My Service in the `Chernomorskii Flot,' 1915-1917 (in Russian), Morskiia Zapiski (The Naval Record) [New York], Vol. X, Nos. 1-3, June/September 1952
  - Womens Club, Mexico, paper read at, 1924
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes
- Miscellany